Finding Aid for Charles Baird Papers, 1892-1933
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles Baird Papers 1892-1933
Baird, Charles, 1870-1944.
85689 Aa 2; UAm
Kansas City, Missouri, banker, first director of athletics, and secretary of the University of Michigan Athletic Association. Correspondence relating to his association with the University of Michigan and its athletic program.
2 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection came from the estate of Charles Baird (donor no. 2119 ) in 1953. Mr. Baird had donated scattered items in 1945 and 1946. Other miscellaneous materials came from the President’s Office (donor no. 87 ) and from Earl L. Rathbun (donor no. 2158 ).
The collection is open to research.
Charles Baird graduated from the University of Michigan in 1895 with both an AB and Ll.B degree. A life-long fan of Michigan athletics, Baird began as student manager of the football team, then in 1898 he was appointed to be the University's first director of athletics, serving until 1910, when he was succeeded by Philip Bartelme. Baird was responsible for hiring Fielding H. Yost as football coach in 1900 and Keene Fitzpatrick as track coach and trainer of the football team.
Although leaving the University for a career in banking in Kansas City, Baird remained devoted to the U-M. In 1935, he donated the needed money for the 51 bells that would make up the Baird Carillon in Burton Tower. He also donated the fountain situated in the mall between Burton Tower and the Michigan League. He died November 30, 1944.
The collection, arranged into two series, Correspondence and Miscellaneous, documents the association of Charles Baird and the University of Michigan, first through his activities as director of athletics and then as active alumnus and benefactor to the University. Much of the correspondence in the collection is with Football coach Fielding H. Yost and track coach and trainer Keene Fitzpatrick.
Subjects:
Baird, Charles, 1870-1944.; Rose Bowl (Football game); University of Michigan. Alumni Association.; Athletic Managers Club (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Football.; University of Notre Dame.; Baird Carillon (University of Michigan)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Baird, Charles, 1870-1944.; Baird family.; Memorabilia.; Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Band.; University of Michigan. Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics.; University of Michigan--Football.; University of Michigan. Law School. Class of 1900.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1891-1900.; University of Michigan--Track and field.
Contributors:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Bartelme, Philip George, 1876-1954.; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Fitzpatrick, Keene, 1865-1944.; Little, Clarence C. (Clarence Cook), b. 1888.; Yost, Fielding Harris, 1871-1946.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series spans the years 1892-1932 and is divided into three subseries: Football Manager and Graduate Director of Athletics, 1892-1909; Keene Fitzpatrick, Fielding Yost and P.G. Bartelme, 1909-1933; and Alumni Affairs, 1916-1933.
  - Football Manager and Graduate Director of Athletics 1892-1909
    The Football Manager and Graduate Director of Athletics subseries covers Baird's years as undergraduate manager of the varsity football team, 1993-1995, and his tenure as director of athletics. Topics covered n the correspondence include arranging of football and other sports schedules; hiring of coaches; athletic relations with other universities and colleges; efforts to organize athletic conferences; intramural and inter-class athletics; the operation of the undergraduate Athletic Association; inter-scholastic (high school) athletics and the championship games sponsored by the Athletic Association; and the development athletic facilities. There is also correspondence with former players commenting on the current state of athletics at the university, recalling events from the player's own career or reporting on their post-Michigan careers. A number of these correspondents had taken jobs coaching at other colleges. One notable letter is from James L.D. Morrison, a member of the 1893 U-M team and the first coach at Notre Dame, describing his efforts to teach the Notre Dame students the basics of football.
    For the years 1901-1909 there is extensive correspondence with football coach Fielding Yost. During this period Yost was on campus only during the Fall football season--residing the rest of the year in Nashville, Tennessee where he had extensive business interests. Baird regularly reported on the football and general athletic situation on campus.
    - 1892-1893 (Box 1)
    - January 1894-May 1894 (Box 1)
    - June 1894-July 1894 (Box 1)
    - August 1894 (Box 1)
    - September 1894 (Box 1)
    - October 1894 (Box 1)
    - November 1894-December 1894 (Box 1)
    - January 1895-March 1895 (Box 1)
    - April 1895-June 1895 (Box 1)
    - July 1895 (Box 1)
    - August 1895 (Box 1)
    - September 1895 (Box 1)
    - October 1895 (Box 1)
    - November-December 1895 (Box 1)
    - January-March 1896 (Box 1)
    - April-July 1896 (Box 1)
    - August-September 1896 (Box 1)
    - October-December 1896 (Box 1)
    - 1897 (Box 1)
    - 1898 (Box 1)
    - 1899 (Box 1)
    - 1900 (Box 1)
    - 1901 (Box 1)
    - Letter from James R.H. Wagner December 11, 1901 (Box 1)
    - 1902 (Box 1)
    - January-August 1903 (Box 1)
    - September-December 1903 (Box 1)
    - 1904 (Box 1)
    - 1905 (Box 1)
    - 1906 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1907 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1907 (Box 1)
    - 1908 (Box 1)
    - January-May 1909 (Box 2)
    - June-July 1909 (Box 2)
    - August-December 1909 (Box 2)
  - Keene Fitzpatrick, Fielding Yost, and P.G. Bartelme 1910-1933
    The Keene Fitzpatrick, Fielding Yost, and P.G. Bartelme, 1910-1933 subseries covers the years after Baird resigned as director of athletics to enter business in Kansas City. Keene Fitzpatrick was track coach and athlete trainer at the University of Michigan, 1898-1910 before moving to Princeton as track coach. Philip Bartelme was Baird's successor as director of athletics, serving until 1920 when Fielding Yost assumed the position.
    - 1910 (Box 2)
    - 1911 (Box 2)
    - 1912 (Box 2)
    - 1913 (Box 2)
    - 1914 (Box 2)
    - 1915 (Box 2)
    - 1916 (Box 2)
    - 1917 (Box 2)
    - 1918 (Box 2)
    - 1919 (Box 2)
    - 1920 (Box 2)
    - 1921 (Box 2)
    - 1922 (Box 2)
    - 1923 (Box 2)
    - 1924 (Box 2)
    - October 1924-May 1925 (Box 2)
    - 1925 (Box 2)
    - 1926 (Box 2)
    - 1927 (Box 2)
    - 1928 (Box 2)
    - 1929 (Box 2)
    - 1930 (Box 2)
    - 1931 (Box 2)
    - 1932 (Box 2)
    - 1933 (Box 2)
  - Alumni Affairs 1916-1932
    Alumni Affairs, 1916-1932 subseries documents Baird's continuing interest in university affairs and his activities in the local club and national Alumni Association. There is some correspondence relating to his donation of funds for the Baird Carillon in Burton Tower and other contributions t the university.
    - 1916-1922 (Box 2)
    - 1923 (Box 2)
    - 1924 (Box 2)
    - 1925 (Box 2)
    - 1926 (Box 2)
    - 1927 (Box 2)
    - 1928 (Box 2)
    - 1929 (Box 2)
    - 1930 (Box 2)
    - 1931 (Box 2)
    - 1932 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous and fragmentary (Box 2)
  - Baird's remarks at the dedication of the Baird Carillon December 4, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - Family photos and portraits (Box 2)
    - Track meet 1901 (Box 2)
      (photo by Charles L. Bliss)
    - Law School Class of 1900 (Box 2)
    - Band circa 1900 (Box 2)
    - Photos circa 1895-1905 (Folder UAm)
      (include football team and players; football souvenir calendars, and miscellaneous University related photos)